Hello and welcome to the first ToMaTo screencast tutorial.
In this tutorial, you will learn how to create and operate your first topology.
An instance of the ToMaTo testbed can be found at http://master.tomato-lab.org
I will now log in to my activated account.
After logging in, we see a list of all topologies of this user.
In this case, this list is empty.
We now have to create a new topology.
We can now populate the empty topology by creating devices.
For devices, we can select between KVM and OpenVZ devices.
As a general rule, you should always select OpenVZ devices if you don't need the benefits that come with KVM.
These newly created devices don't have any network connections yet.
In this example, we will simply connect them to each other.
Now, we can prepare the topology.
This means that the testbed will create the virtual machines
and their initial disk images.
The red 'stop' signs on the devices indicate that preparing has been finished.
We can now proceed to booting the devices.
When the devices have been started successfully, a green 'started' icon will appear on the devices.
In this tutorial, we will run a ping test to demonstrate the network functionality.
To do this, we first need the IP address of the left device.
Each network interface of a device appears as a grey dot.
You can get the IP address of a network interface from its configuration window.
We can get VNC access to a device's console via its right-click menu.
Using 'ifconfig', you can show the device's network configuration.
In this case, there should be one ethernet interface, and one loopback interface.
Using the 'ping' command, we can run a ping test to the IP address we have discovered before.
After completing our tests, we should now clean up.
First, we have to stop our devices.
This means that the virtual machines will be stopped, but they are not destroyed, and the disk images will be kept.
Since we don't need our devices anymore, we can destroy them.
This means that the virtual machines and the disk images are deleted from the server.
We won't be using this topology anymore, so we can delete it.
We have now completed the first screencast tutorial.
In this tutorial, we have created a first topology consisting of two devices.
We have started them, and then run a ping test between them.
Since you haven't seen all aspects of ToMaTo by now, I highly recommend you to work through the more specialized tutorials available at tomato-lab.org